Lucas Veras

lucasdsveras@gmail.com lveras.com github.com/verasls +351 918 119 324 R Dr Afonso Cordeiro 588, Matosinhos, Portugal ↑

Curriculum Vitae



I'm a 28 years old brazilian guy, who loves sports, living in Porto for over 5 years. During my time in Portugal, I have complete a Master's degree and I'm currently in the final strech of my PhD. Throughout my academic journey I have learned a set of abilities related to solving problems and generating insights from data using scientific and programming tools, and that turned out to be my favorite part of the job. Nowadays, my main carreer objective is to act as a full-time data scientist in order to put into practice in the job market the knowlodge and skills acquired during my Master's and PhD.

✓ Technical skills

Programming R (expert), Python (advanced), MATLAB (advanced), Bash (intermediate), SQL (intermediate), C++ (advanced beginner)

Tools Git/GitHub, Make, continuous integration, unit testing

Education

2023 - Ongoing BS in Computer Science, Faculty Estácio of Alagoas

Maceió, Brasil

2019 - Ongoing PhD in Physical Activity and Health, Faculty of Sports, University of Porto

• Porto, Portugal

• Focused on developing prediction models based on data from wearable devices to quantify physical activity related to bone health

2017 - 2019 MSc in Physical Activity and Health, Faculty of Sports, University of Porto

• Porto, Portugal

• Thesis: Calibration and validation of accelerometers: Establishing new equations for energy expenditure and ground reaction force prediction

2012 - 2015 BS in Physical Education, Faculty Estácio of Alagoas

♥ Maceió, Brasil

Professional experience

2021 - Ongoing Freelance statistical consulting

- Conducting statistical hypothesis tests to draw inference from data
- Generating reports of scientific activity through literate programming

2019 - Ongoing PhD in Physical Activity and Health, Faculty of Sports, University of Porto ◆ Porto, Portugal

- Generating reports of scientific activity through literate programming
- Fitting prediction and classification models with statistical/machine learning techniques
- Conducting statistical hypothesis tests to draw inference from data
- Extracting, gathering and organizing data from multiple sources (e.g., spreadsheets, reports in pdf files, websites)
- Making visualizations to see trends, relationships and get insights from data
- Processing biological signals derived from wearable devices
- Modeling time series data
- 2017 2019 MSc in Physical Activity and Health, Faculty of Sports, University of Porto
 - Porto, Portugal
 - Same experiences as described above

Courses

- 2023 Ongoing Python Object-Oriented Programming (OOP): Beginner to Pro, Udemy Online
- 2023 Ongoing Machine Learning A-Z, Udemy
 - Online
 - 2020 2020 Introduction to data analysis and image processing with MATLAB, Institute for Research and Innovation in Health (i3S), University of Porto
 - Porto, Portugal

Languages

- Portuguese, native
- **English**, fluent (spoken and written)

Q Awards

- 2023 Top Cited Article 2021-2022 in Obesity Science & Practice, Wiley
- 2022 Best Communication in Physical Activity, 26th Portuguese Congress of Obesity
- 2021 Best Communication in Physical Activity, 25th Portuguese Congress of Obesity
- 2021 Student Sponsorship, ActiGraph Digital Data Summit
- 2020 **Best Oral Communication in Sports Sciences**, 13th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto
- 2019 Prize for Best Work in Physical Activity, 23th Portuguese Congress of Obesity

Scientific papers

2023 Using raw accelerometer data to predict high-impact mechanical loading.

Sensors

Veras L, Diniz-Sousa F, Boppre G, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Vilas-Boas JP, Machado L, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2023 Multicompartment body composition analysis in older adults: a cross-sectional study.

BMC Geriatrics

Rossini-Venturini AC, **Veras L**, Pugliesi Abdalla P, Pereira dos Santos A, Tasinafo-Junior MF, Santos Lopes da Silva L, Cândido Alves T, Ferriolli E, Romo-Perez V, Garcia-Soidan JL, Mota J, Lopes Machado DR

2022 Mechanical loading prediction through accelerometry data during walking and running.

European Journal of Sport Science

Veras L, Diniz-Sousa F, Boppre G, Resende-Coelho A, Moutinho-Ribeiro E, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Vilas-Boas JP, Machado L, Oliveira J, Fonseca H

2022 Changes in volumetric bone mineral density and bone quality after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: A meta-analysis with meta-regression.

Obesity Reviews

Hernández-Martínez A, **Veras L**, Boppre G, Soriano-Maldonado A, Oliveira J, Diniz-Souza F, Fonseca H.

2022 Comparison of Climacteric Symptoms, Quality of Life, and Self-Care Attitudes before and during the COVID-19 Pandemic.

Journal of Menopausal Medicine

Oliveira Serra C, Gomes Leite PM, Bezerra AB, Freitas L, **Veras L**, Deda Costa M, Conceição Gonçalves LL, Yung dos Santos Maciel L

2022 Effects of a Multicomponent Exercise Training Program on Balance Following Bariatric Surgery.

International Journal of Sports Medicine

Diniz-Souza F, Granja T, Boppre G, **Veras L**, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas-Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2022 Does Exercise Improve the Cardiometabolic Risk Profile of Patients with Obesity After Bariatric Surgery? A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.

Obesity Surgery

Boppre G, Diniz-Sousa F, Veras L, Oliveira J, Fonseca H

2022 The Effect of Exercise for the Prevention of Bone Mass Loss After Bariatric Surgery: a Systematic Review and Meta-analysis.

Obesity Surgery

Diniz-Sousa F, Boppre G, Veras L, Hernández-Martínez A, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2021 The effect of bariatric surgery on gravitational loading and its impact on bone mass.

Bone

Diniz-Sousa F, **Veras L**, Boppre G, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas-Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2021 Can exercise promote additional benefits on body composition in patients with obesity after bariatric surgery? A systematic review and meta-analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.

 $Obesity\ Science\ \ \ \ Practice$

Boppre G, Diniz-Sousa F, Veras L, Oliveira J, Fonseca H

2021 How Does Bariatric Surgery Affect Fall Risk Factors?.

Obesity Surgery

Diniz-Sousa F, **Veras L**, Boppre G, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas-Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2021 Wearable Devices for Physical Activity and Healthcare Monitoring in Elderly People: A Critical Review.

Geriatrics

Teixeira E, Fonseca H, Diniz-Sousa F, **Veras L**, Boppre G, Oliveira J, Pinto D, Alves AJ, Barbosa A, Mendes R, Marques-Aleixo I.

2021 The Effect of an Exercise Intervention Program on Bone Health After Bariatric Surgery: A Randomized Controlled Trial.

Journal of Bone and Mineral Research

Diniz-Sousa F, **Veras L**, Boppre G, Sa-Couto P, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas- Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2020 Accelerometer-based prediction of skeletal mechanical loading during walking in normal weight to severely obese subjects.

 $Osteoporosis\ International$

Veras L, Diniz-Sousa F, Boppre G, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas-Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.

2020 Accelerometry calibration in people with class II-III obesity: Energy expenditure prediction and physical activity intensity identification.

Gait and Posture

Diniz-Sousa F, **Veras L**, Ribeiro JC, Boppre G, Devezas V, Santos-Sousa H, Preto J, Machado L, Vilas-Boas JP, Oliveira J, Fonseca H.